Agriculture has
a significant effect
on greenhouse gasses.
What foods and diets are best
for reducing that impact?
Check it out.
"Which Foods and Diets Have
the Lowest Carbon Footprint?"
Our eating habits are making us and
the planet increasingly unhealthy.
Ours is a lose-lose situation;
a global transformation of the
food system is urgently needed.
In consideration of the mounting evidence
regarding the environmental effects of
foods, for the 2015 to 2020 U.S. Dietary
Guidelines the scientific advisory
committee included for the first time
a chapter focused on food safety
and sustainability, concluding,
"a dietary pattern that is higher
in plant-based foods,
such as vegetables, fruits,
whole grains, legumes,
nuts, and seeds,
and lower in animal-based foods,
is not only more health promoting
but also associated with lesser
environmental impact..."
Despite unprecedented public support,
this and other sustainability language
was, not surprisingly, vanished
from the final Dietary Guidelines
published jointly by the U.S. Department
of Agriculture. They're not even
sufficiently sticking to the science on
healthy eating either, including no, or
too lax limits for animal-source foods,
despite the available evidence.
Even if they ignored planetary health
altogether and just stuck to the latest
evidence on healthy eating, it would
have knock-on environmental benefits.
Replacing animal-source foods with
plant-based ones would not only
improve nutrition and
help people live longer,
but could reduce greenhouse
gas emissions up to 84%.
In general, plant-based foods cause
fewer adverse environmental effects
by nearly any measure. In terms of
carbon footprint, all the foods that are
the equivalent of driving more than a
mile per serving are animal products.
Here's the greenhouse gas
emissions from various foods.
Even though something like a lamb
chop or farmed fish may be the worst,
eating chicken still causes like
five times the global warming
than even something like tropical fruit,
though the climate superstars
are legumes—beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils.
For example, in the United States,
substituting beans for beef
at the national level could alone deliver
up to 75% of the 2020 greenhouse gas
emissions reduction target and
spare an area of land 1.5 times
the size of California, not to
mention the health benefits.
And it's not just greenhouse gases.
Kidney beans required approximately
18 times less land, 10 times less water,
9 times less fuel, 12 times less fertilizer,
and 10 times less pesticides. So
yeah, according to the prestigious
EAT-Lancet Commission, more
plant-based may be better,
but even a shift towards a healthier
dietary pattern emphasizing whole grains,
fruits, vegetables, nuts, and
legumes without necessarily
eating strictly-plant-based,
would be beneficial.
In Europe, for example, just halving the
consumption of meat, dairy, and eggs
would achieve up to a 40% reduction in
nitrogen emissions and greenhouse gas
emissions, and require about a fifth less
land. In addition, the dietary changes
would also lower health risks,
reducing cardiovascular mortality,
their leading cause of death.
Note, however, that minimizing
environmental impacts does not
necessarily maximize human health.
Yes, animal products, dairy, eggs, fish,
and other meat releases significantly
more greenhouse gas per
serving than foods from plants;
eating added sugar and oil isn't going
to do your own body any favors.
In California, including more animal
products in your diet requires
an additional 10,000
quarts of water a week.
So that's like taking 150
more showers a week.
Even just skipping meat on weekdays
could conserve thousands of gallons
a week compared to eating meat
every day, and cut your daily
carbon footprint and total
ecological footprint by about 40%.
Some countries are actually
doing something about it.
The Chinese government, for example,
has outlined a plan to reduce
its citizens' meat consumption by 50%,
whereas much of the rest of the world
appears to be doing the complete
opposite, pumping billions
of taxpayer dollars into subsidizing
the meat, dairy, and egg industries.
We can certainly all try to do our part;
however, an obstacle to dietary change
may be consumers' underestimation
of the environmental impacts
of different types of food, but
may be aided by labeling.
For example, imagine picking up a can
of a beef noodle soup and seeing this.
The carbon footprint of
a single half-cup serving
is like leaving a light on
for 39 hours straight.
And not some eco-bulb, right? An
old-school 100-watt hot incandescent,
compared to a meat-free vegetable
soup—a difference of 34 light-bulb hours.
You can imagine someone getting on your
case for unnecessarily leaving on a light
for 34 minutes, but this is 34 hours
just eating a different half cup of soup.
In what “was arguably the largest
ever environmental protest
in the world,” more than a
million children, across more than
a hundred countries, joined
a “Global Climate March,
demanding that governments act…”
“The concerns of the young
protesters are justified”
and “supported by the
best available science,”
wrote a group of
scientists and scholars.
The enormous mobilization shows
that young people have at least
understood the situation, and
“we strongly support their demand
for rapid and forceful action.”
In terms of our food supply there
are all sorts of little tweaks,
like feed additives that
can reduce cattle belching,
but put all those tweaks together,
according to the prestigious
EAT-Lancet Commission, and
we’re only talking about
reducing agricultural greenhouse-
gas emissions in 2050
by about 10% ; whereas, if
we instead switched over
to plant foods, we “could reduce
emissions by up to 80 percent.”
All those cow, sheep, and goat
burps only represent a fraction
of the greenhouse gas emissions
from animal agriculture;
so, that’s why according to the IPCC,
the official Intergovernmental
Panel on Climate Change, becoming
a so-called climate carnivore,
just cutting down on
ruminant products like beef,
wouldn’t reduce greenhouse
gas emissions as much
as eating a healthier diet and
limiting meat across the board.
And, the fewer animal
products the better.
“Which diet has the least environmental
impact on our planet?”
A systematic review found that
eating completely plant-based
may be “the optimal diet
for the environment.”
But it’s not all or nothing.
Even just cutting down on meat
to under an ounce or two
a day could get you half
the way there in terms of
reducing greenhouse gas emissions.
In terms of land use, a healthier
diet, like a Mediterranean diet,
may decrease your footprint by
about a quarter, whereas even more
plant-based diets can
drop land use 50% or more.
In general, diets that
include meat require
about three times more water,
13 times more fertilizer,
more than twice the energy,
and 40% more pesticides
than those that don’t.
If you look even broader at
the total environmental impact
of omnivorous versus
vegetarian versus vegan diets,
looking not just at global warming,
but ocean acidification,
agricultural run-off, smog,
ecotoxicity of the water and soil,
and direct human toxicity
of the air we breathe
and the water we drink, and
the soil we grow our food from,
eating eggs and dairy may be
nine times worse than plants.
And, eating eggs, dairy, and
meat may be 17 times worse
than sticking to plant foods.
Oh, and as a bonus, we could feed
an additional 350 million Americans,
like an entire extra
country’s worth of people—
more than if we eliminated
food waste completely.
Changing meat-eating habits
would seem to be a relatively
cheap and easy way to
mitigate climate change,
in contrast to many other
factors outside our control.
However, surveys suggest few
seem to recognize this option
of eating less meat as a
signiﬁcant opportunity for helping.
Research has shown that
consumers often underestimate
the impacts of meat consumption
on the environment in general,
and on climate change in particular.
“The outstanding effectiveness
of the less meat option
(as established by climate
experts) was recognized by…
[only] 6% of [Americans sampled,]
and that’s after they were
prompted to assume climate
change is actually happening.
“There is an overwhelming
scientific consensus that
climate change is real and
that we’re driving it,”
but only about half of
U.S. adults believe it.
This is not by coincidence.
Just like the tobacco industry
tried to subvert the
overwhelming evidence that
smoking caused cancer, companies
like “Exxon orchestrated
climate change denial
campaign[s] that stalled
meaningful efforts… for decades.”
Certainly, environmental groups
should know better, though.
“None of the highest profile
NGOs examined” appeared to want
to feature the link between meat
consumption and climate change.
They were all aware of
the evidence, of course,
but evidently the science
alone was not sufﬁcient.
It’s like another form of
denialism that can become like
a negative feedback loop, where
it’s not popular to talk about,
so you don’t talk about it,
so it remains not popular
to talk about, depriving
the issue of the attention
that it needs to break out.
And when they have messaged
about it, environmental groups
have tended to favor just
asking for a moderate reduction
in meat consumption,
notable given the research
demonstrating how much more
powerful a lever it could be
at the individual level
to go even further.
But, they don’t want to be seen
as telling people what to do,
instead advocating for small
changes, like turning off
your computer monitor at
lunchtime or printing double-sided.
But, “the cumulative impact of
large numbers of individuals
making [just] marginal improvements
in their environmental impact”
may end up constituting just a
marginal collective improvement.
Yet, we now live at a
time when we need to make
urgent and ambitious changes.